UGURCAN CAKAL, M.Sc.

Software Engineer

Zürich, Switzerland (B-permit) •

ugurcan.cakal@gmail.com

github.com/ugurcancakal

linkedin.com/in/ugurcancakal

I'm a self-motivated engineer, based in Zürich, with a knack for computers and electronics. I have hands-on experience in hardware-aware software development, especially in areas like machine learning, autonomous robotics, and embedded systems. Adapting to the situation, I can be a strong team player or a one-person army

SKILLS

Python (Expert), C++ (Proficient), C, CUDA, Verilog, ARM Assembly (Competent) **Programming**

Machine Learning PyTorch, Jax, TensorFlow, sckit-learn, xNNs, SNNs, MLFlow, pruning, quantization, event-driven Git, Linux, CI-CD, Docker, Kubernetes, DevOps, MLOps, unit test, verification, optimization **Software**

Language English(C1), Turkish (Native), German (B1)

Soft Communication, problem-solving, adaptability, resilience, agility, attention to detail

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

SynSense AG Zürich, Switzerland ML Algorithms and Applications Engineer July 2022 - Present

Led the implementation of application software support for digital neuromorphic Xylo, and mixed-signal neuromorphic Dynap-SE2 chips. Offline simulation, hardware-in-the loop, SNN training and mapping, sim-to-real.

- Trained and deployed application prototypes targeting various Xylo chip families, some of which are human activity detection with IMU signals, and background noise classification with audio signals.
- Spearheaded the development and maintenance of Rockpool, an open-source python package for developing signal processing applications with spiking neural networks. Currently ranking as the first contributor (~2,000 commits).
- Composed comprehensive user manuals and tutorials and delivered presentations to stakeholders.

SynSense AG (Remote) Zürich, Switzerland

Software Engineer (Intern)

Jun 2021 – June 2022

- Modeled the jax-backend time efficient custom hardware simulator, simulating VLSI dynamics of Dynap-SE2 chip.
- Improved BPTT training pipeline execution time from 10s of days to 10s of minutes with just-in-time compilation.
- Implemented non-uniform quantization, custom gradient computation, mismatch simulation algorithms to solve hardware mapping problem for analog mixed signal Dynap-SE2 processor.
- Developed an efficient application deployment pipeline which significantly reduced the required effort for an application development: from an entire PhD thesis to an internship project.

GOHM (Remote) Istanbul, Turkey January 2021 – April 2021

Machine Learning Engineer (Contract)

Engineered a deep convolutional neural network application from scratch, enabling efficient processing of lowdimensional RF signals to detect analog device fingerprints for edge inference on the NVIDIA Jetson board.

EDUCATION

Middle East Technical University

Ankara, Turkey

Master of Electrical and Electronics Engineering GPA: (3.79/4.0) September 2019 – August 2022

- Courses taken: Neurocomputers and Deep Learning, Applied Parallel Programming on GPU, Artificial Intelligence
- Thesis: DynapSIM: A Fast, Optimizable, and Mismatch Aware Mixed-Signal Neuromorphic Chip Simulator

Middle East Technical University

Ankara, Turkey

Bachelor of Electrical and Electronics Engineering GPA: (3.28/4.0) September 2014 – June 2019

Courses taken: Microprocessors, Computer Architecture I & II, Computational Intelligence, Machine Learning

PROJECTS

DVS Gesture Classification

METU, Ankara, Turkey

Machine Learning, Computer Vision

November 2020 – January 2021

Benchmarked two CNNs (3D-CNN, CRNN) using PyTorch on IBM DVS128 gesture dataset.

Developed a custom AER event processing framework for event-based cameras.

Eye Tracking

Embedded Sytems, Computer Vision

ADM Tronics, New Jersey, USA

December 2020 – January 2021

Engineered a real-time application to detect, track and overlay a human pupil and iris using an active-IR camera

Chase and Tag Robot, B.Sc. Capstone Design Project

METU, Ankara, Turkey

Robotics, Computer Vision

October 2018 - June 2019

- Designed and assembled a cost-effective autonomous robot car capable of chasing another robot along a closed path and tagging the opponent, with a vision-based motion planning algorithm, and an ad-hoc Wi-Fi communication.
- Authored comprehensive documentation including conceptual design, critical design review, implementation reports, and a user manual, demonstrating attention to detail and thorough project documentation capabilities.

Custom MIPS Architecture Design

METU, Ankara, Turkey

Computer Architecture

February 2019 - June 2019

Implemented a single cycle and a multi cycle MIPS processor using Verilog HDL with automated test benches

Classification for Detection of FOD

ArgosAl, Ankara, Turkey

Machine Learning, Computer Vision

November 2018 - January 2019

Built and deployed a convolutional neural network using TensorFlow, which can classify foreign object debris on the
airport pavements as bird, metal, and plastic; using a proprietary dataset provided by ArgosAl company.

Battleship Game Console

METU, Ankara, Turkey

Embedded Systems

November 2018 - January 2019

Remodeled the famous game Battleship on TM4C123G Board and NOKIA 5110 LCD Screen using assembly language

NON-TECHNICAL

- **Chaired** METU Amateur Photograph club for 2 years between 2015 2017 organizing several workshops, exhibitions, artist talks and initiating several tenders.
- Tutored high-school students for university entrance exams for 5 years between 2013 2018.
- Interested in analog photography, modern art, home-brewing, board games, and calisthenics.